I need to start by telling you about the
alarm.
Every Monday morning at 11:30 in my
hometown of Plymouth, a siren rings out
from the Devport Royal dockyard. It's a
proper classic warning siren, and it is
loud. It echoes around the city.
Throughout the course of my life, it's
punctuated maths lessons, work meetings,
family occasions, walks in the park. For
everyone who lives here, it's a weirdly
normal part of weekly life. People
living here close to Devonport dockyard
have grown used to this sound, but they
hope this is the only time they'll ever
get to hear it. I say weird because the
weekly sounding of that alarm is a test.
A test to prepare for nuclear emergency.
See, one of the Devport Royal dockyard's
roles is as a repair and refitting base
for the UK's four Vanguard class
submarines, which when not in Plymouth
or in their full-time home in Scotland,
patrol the ocean as the UK's continuous
atsea nuclear deterrent. Each submarine
can be armed with up to 16 Trident 2 D5
ballistic [music] missiles, each with a
range of up to 7,500 m and armed with a
payload up to six times as powerful as
that which was dropped on Hiroshima in
1945.
Yet, it's not in anticipation of nuclear
strike that the siren exists. The real
fear is of a radiation leak from one of
the nuclear reactors from which the
submarines draw their power during their
long, lonely missions. This risk is
increased by the presence of a so-called
nuclear [music] graveyard in which 13
unused submarines, some of which have
been out of action for more than 30
years, sit with their reactors still
intact, waiting for the government to
cough up the cash to decommission them.
Growing up, all of this felt quite quite
a little bit kit, maybe. The Cold War
was long since over and nuclear
submarines felt as much an anacronism as
Blitz Tea Parties or Civil War battle
reenactments. But last year, Russian
propagandist and broadcaster Efghani
Popov took to the airwaves of the
state-run YA channel and listed [music]
off what Vladimir Putin's targets might
be in the event of a nuclear exchange.
Manchester.
>> And look, I always appreciate seeing my
hometown on TV, even if it is as part of
an apocalyptic prediction. But recently,
the chances of that prediction coming
true haven't seemed as remote as they
once did.
[music]
>> [music]
>> This is the New Star Treaty or to give
it its official title, the treaty
between the United States of America and
the Russian Federation on measures for
the further reduction and limitation of
strategic offensive arms. At time of
recording, it is the last remaining
treaty limiting the number of nuclear
weapons [music] in the world. Signed in
April 2010 by Barack Obama and then
Russian President Dmitri Medvidev, it
places a hard cap on the number of nukes
that both Russia and America can have
deployed at any one time. The cap of
1550 nuclear warheads might sound like
quite a lot, but it represented the
fewest nuclear weapons those countries
had ever had ready to fire at one
another at any one time. In February
2026, which by the time you're watching
this might be now, that changes because
on the 4th of that month, this treaty
runs out.
>> We're [snorts] about to live in the in a
world where strategic nuclear weapons of
the two greatest nuclear powers are
uncapped.
>> This is Elelliana Johns. Elelliana is a
senior research associate [music] for
the Nuclear Information Project at the
Federation of American Scientists. The
history of our organization is actually
pretty interesting. So we were founded
in 1945 by some of the uh scientists who
participated in the Manhattan project.
So from that legacy, uh, my team works
on kind of the way we like to frame it
is we we like to we're trying to pull
back the curtain on nuclear secrecy
because nuclear weapons really are able
to thrive in secrecy when they're not
talked about, when they're when they're
when they're uh hidden from the public
view, from public scrutiny. Elelliana
has written extensively on the past,
present, and future of nuclear weapons.
And so, she seemed like the perfect
person to fill me in on what the ending
of this crucial treaty actually means.
>> It will be the first time in more than
50 years that the United States and
Russia or I guess the former Soviet
Union are not bound by some form of
strategic arms control arrangement or
engaged in [music]
um dialogue about um their nuclear
weapons. What that means is after the
treaty expires, the US and Russia won't
be bound or obligated by any agreement.
So they'll have the capacity to upload
hundreds and hundreds of nuclear
warheads
if they don't decide to continue abiding
by these treaty limits um or if they
don't reach some other form of
agreement.
>> There couldn't be a worse time for this
to be happening. One of the reasons that
this treaty is expiring in the first
place is that geopolitical tensions are
currently desperately high. And I wrote
that line before the US kidnaps Maduro.
And whatever the other major military
world event is, which happens between us
filming this, editing it, and getting
out.
On top of all of that other stuff,
countries are increasingly turning to
nuclear weapons to show their might.
>> I [music] think you probably hear people
talking about this new nuclear age that
we're in. We're in a new environment
that we haven't really experienced
before. Nuclear weapons are kind of
coming to the forefront of media of of
um policy conversations once again.
>> Evani Popob's veiled threat to bomb my
house followed a stream of saber
rattling from Putin himself. Ever since
he launched his invasion of Ukraine in
February 2022, the Russian president has
barely shut up about his nuclear
weapons. He's both lowered the threshold
at which Russia says it will use its
nukes and gifted a number of tactical
nuclear weapons to its ally Bellarus. As
recently as October, he announced a new
underwater nuclear drone called Poseidon
which he claimed could put entire states
out of operation.
Never one to be outlasted, Donald Trump
soon took to Truth Social to announce
that the US would be resuming nuclear
testing.
>> Other countries are testing. We're the
only country that doesn't test and I
want to be I don't want to be the only
country that doesn't test.
>> Although Energy Secretary Chris Wright
soon caveed that this wouldn't involve
actual nuclear detonations. [music]
China, meanwhile, has doubled the size
of its nuclear arsenal since 2020. And
even the UK has been upping its game,
recently announcing that it would be
buying 12 F-35A planes capable of
carrying American nuclear gravity bombs.
>> It [music] marks the return of the RAF
to nuclear deterrence for the first time
in three decades, representing the
biggest strengthening of our deterrence
posture in a generation. There are
proliferation concerns in several
countries um that are quite serious and
there are threats and potential
preparations for returning to nuclear
testing. All of these are [music] are
factors that characterize this new
nuclear age that we're in um and really
heighten the risks of nuclear use in a
way that we haven't seen in the past
[music] few few decades. All of this has
been accompanied by a glut of nuclear
storytelling in books, on TV, and at the
cinema. These narratives, however,
sometimes imply that our current nuclear
situation in the real world is a simple
return to the state of play as it
existed at the height of the Cold War.
In today's video, I want to explore the
various ways in which our current teeter
on the edge of the nuclear precipice
both [music] is and isn't different to
before, and the three things which put
us at most risk of tipping over the
edge.
>> [music]
>> The great irony of the position we're
currently in is that when it comes to
trying to rid the world of nuclear
weapons, we were doing so, so well. I
mean, the gains were first made in the
sort of the 50s and 60s um with the
the huge level of opposition to nuclear
testing.
>> This is Sophie Bolt, general secretary
of the campaign for nuclear disarmament.
We, you know, we're a very long-standing
um peace organization that people might
um might know from the s of the peace uh
symbol, this very iconic [music] peace
symbol which is um semaphore for CND for
you [music] know campaign for nuclear
disarmament.
>> The CND was founded in 1958 after the UK
tested its first successful hydrogen
bomb on Christmas Island. you know,
people were terrified that they were
going to be absorbing, you know, it was
sort of radiation and they were going to
be, you know, passing on to their
children and what have you. So, like
there was a huge huge massive
mobilization. In fact, that's partly how
CND came into existence.
>> As Sophie explained, the path to this
treaty was forged way back in 1963 with
the signing of this treaty, the partial
test [music] ban treaty. Let me show you
something. In the 18 years since the
testing of the first nuclear device, the
world's total nuclear stockpiles had
risen from the initial three developed
by the Manhattan Project to a whopping
32,648.
Developing these weapons had involved
hundreds of tests, each with devastating
effects on the environment. They were
also unpredictable. [music] The 1954
Castle Bravo test, the largest ever
undertaken by the US military, had
turned out to be twice as powerful as
researchers had thought and ended up
killing a Japanese fisherman. [music]
There were also horrific consequences
for the military personnel involved in
carrying out these tests.
>> What a lot of people might have heard
about is the nuclear test veterans. you
know, these were kind of British troops
um who were treated like you know,
guinea pigs and made to sit um and you
know, so physically experienced um
nuclear explosions and of course [music]
suffered you know horrific um you know
consequences
>> in response to campaigns and marches
like those organized by the CND. Then
the Soviet Union, the United States and
the United Kingdom agreed to ban all
future overground testing of nuclear
devices. So that was like saying we will
not allow any um explosions.
>> The results were pretty immediate. Over
the next 5 years, the rate at which
nuclear warheads were being developed
slowed significantly. In 1968 actually
saw a slight decrease from just over
40,000 nuclear warheads being available
to use in the world to 39,500.
This was just in time for the signing of
this treaty, the nuclear
non-prololiferation treaty, which at
least in theory bans non-uclear
countries from becoming so.
>> It's a deal in a way between the nuclear
states [music] and the non-nuclear
states because the deal is that the
nuclear weapons states will get rid of
their nuclear weapons and the non-uclear
states will not get any nuclear weapons.
The actual disarmament part of the
treaty was more of an ambition than a
commitment. More concrete was the manner
in which the non-proliferation treaty
worked to avoid an arms race in terms of
the number of countries which had
nuclear weapons through freezing it at
the five nations which had already built
and tested a bomb. At this point, these
were the United States, the Soviet
Union, the UK, France, and China. The
treaty hasn't been entirely successful
in this. India, Israel, and Pakistan
never signed and have since developed
nuclear weapons. or North Korea pulled
out in 2003. Whatever its limitations,
however, the fact that there are still
only nine countries in the world with
nuclear weapons, we don't find ourselves
in a situation where every country has a
bunch of nukes pointed at every other is
largely attributable to this document.
The fact it was signed way back in 1970
also goes to show how quickly nuclear
weapons came to be seen as a particular
type of weapon different to any other.
And they these weapons are so horrific.
Um when you look at the um destructive
power, but also what they do to human
beings um they are so destructive um
that the the way in which they kind of
kill people is so horrific [music]
um that they have no place um in a
civilized society. By the early 1970s,
the two main nuclear powers, [music] the
US and the Soviet Union, were already
looking at how to place hard caps on the
number of nuclear weapons that each had
pointed at the other. Soviet warhead
production was really getting into full
swing at this point. And in fact, the
total number of warheads had gone up
once again to just under 42,000.
And it's against this backdrop that this
treaty was signed, the anti-bballistic
missile treaty. Rather than limiting the
number of nuclear weapons that each
country could have pointed at the other,
Richard Nixon and Leon Brev agreed to
reduce the level of defense that each of
their countries had against potential
nuclear attack by the other. At the
time, the US and the USSR had been
building complexes of interceptor
systems designed to destroy incoming
nuclear missiles before they could reach
their target. This had a significant
downside, however, in that it risked
accelerating the nuclear arms race even
further. seek the easiest way to
overcome these interceptor systems is
simply to chuck more nuclear weapons at
them than they can stop. The concern
then was that as each nuclear
superpower's defenses got better, the
other would build more nukes in an
unstoppable escalation. The
anti-bballistic missile treaty thus saw
the US and the Soviet Union make the
genuinely brave decision to limit
themselves to just two interceptor
complexes [music] with just 100
anti-bballistic missiles in each. More
than just the specific defenses that
this treaty placed on each country's
nuclear defenses, however, Nixon's trip
to Moscow also proved that an ever
[music] escalating nuclear arms race
wasn't inevitable. In fact, the same
series of talks led to the signing of
this treaty, which is perhaps the
closest to genuine nuclear disarmament
we ever got. The strategic arms
limitations treaty or sort two to its
friends [music] was signed in Vienna in
1979.
This time by Brev and Jimmy Carter.
Reducing both countries stockpiles would
have seen the total number of warheads
in the world go from more than 53,000
[music]
to around about five. Unfortunately,
it wasn't to be. The dream of Salt 2
quickly turned into a nightmare when the
USSR invaded Afghanistan. Any sense that
the Cold War could soon be over
evaporated and rather than the number of
nuclear weapons falling, they [music]
continued to climb. That is until 1987
because that December something
incredible happened. The first was the
signing of this treaty, [music] the
intermediate range nuclear forces
treaty. This saw the US and USSR agree
to actively destroy all of their ground
launched ballistic missiles with ranges
between 1,000 and 5,000 km regardless of
whether they were nuclear or
conventionally armed.
>> So there was obviously a huge amount of
um international pressure to [music]
make you know Russia and the US get rid
of these of nuclear weapons. But it was
the huge protests [music] in Britain and
across Europe specifically against these
missiles like these cruise mass
missiles, these long range missiles that
were so dangerous that forced for
instance [music] you know Reagan to sign
up to that treaty and to um to literally
destroy you know thousands [music] of
these long range missiles. So, and that
was because of again like literally
people you know signing the petitions
like you know going on the demos and and
speaking [music] out.
>> Both countries retained their largest
so-called strategic missiles capable of
traveling halfway around the globe. But
the scrapping of these shorter range
missiles meant a significant reduction
in the number of Soviet and American
missiles being placed in Europe [music]
drastically cooling tensions. The
biggest turnaround however came in
overall stocks. The year 1987 [music]
marks the first year in nearly two
decades that the number of nuclear
weapons in the world [music] at that
December was lower than it had been the
previous January. The nuclear arms race
was effectively [music]
over and the number of warheads in the
world was about to spiral downwards and
[music] downwards. Between just 1986 and
1991, the world would shed 15,000
warheads. [music] an unthinkable decline
which would have been unthinkable just a
few years earlier.
The real stake in the heart of what's
sometimes called the first nuclear age,
however, came in 1991 [music] with the
signing of this bad boy, the Strategic
Arms Reduction Treaty or START. [music]
>> That again is a is a a bilateral treaty
between the two, you know, massive, you
know, nuclear powers. Start didn't go
quite as far as Sulk 2 would have in its
limits on nuclear warheads, but it did
commit both the US and what was about to
become the Russian Federation to having
no more than 1,600 nuclear armed bombs
or missiles deployed at any one time.
It's hard to get across just how much of
a massive victory all of this is for
international diplomacy. The START
treaty [music] sent the world's stocks
of nuclear warheads into nearly terminal
decline. By 2009, there had [music] been
an 82% reduction in the number of
nuclear warheads hanging [music] bound
in the world, making the chances of
mutually assured destruction lower than
ever. It just goes to show that in the
right time and with the right context,
diplomacy [music] works.
Unfortunately,
it wasn't to last.
>> [music]
>> my heart.
[music]
Here we go. Okay, so earlier on I
promised to tell you some of the key
things which have changed since the
height of the Cold War and today. The
first is that the scariest bombs today
often aren't the biggest. It's quite
popular in news reports and online
videos about nuclear weapons to
hyperfixate on how much larger the
explosive power of the nuclear missiles
we have today is compared to the bomb
dropped on Hiroshima. And we could do
that. We could talk more about the carel
bravo and sar bomber tests. We could
pull up Alex Wallstein's excellent nuke
map and [music] see what the damage
would be if a Russian RS24 landed on
Devonport Dockyard. Oh, I am so dead.
But we really need to talk about smiles.
>> Lowy yield nuclear weapons are not a new
issue. They've been around since the
very beginning. And the thought of using
low yield nuclear weapons on the
battlefield battlefield or for military
purposes really came about early on
after the first nuclear weapons were
used. See, while a perception of nuclear
weapons as an entirely different
category of weapon to a handgun,
artillery piece, or conventional torpedo
did emerge reasonably quickly, there
remained some military leaders who
continued to see nukes as in many ways
just a big bomb. And big bombs could be
useful. In 1953, the US Army started
rolling out its MGR1 Honest John
rockets, which were effectively just an
artillery unit. You point it in the
direction of the enemy, press fire,
banner launcher throws at them. The only
difference is that instead of a
conventional shell, what land is a
nuclear warhead with a yield somewhere
between 2 and 30 kilotons. [music] The
US, UK, and Soviet Union all also
developed nuclear depth charges designed
to be dropped from ships in order to
destroy submarines. Guided torpedoes
weren't particularly sophisticated at
this point, and so the thought was that
you could considerably increase the
chances of destroying a submarine if you
just set off a 32 koton nuke in the
general vicinity. All of this obviously
sounds incredibly slapstick. In fact,
both of the video games I can think of,
which involve tactical nukes, do so as a
kind of joke. So, obviously, the
original version of this was going to be
that I was going to be playing Modern
Warfare 2 and then I was going to go
with the killstreaks and then I was
going to drop the tactical nuke.
However, couldn't get Modern War 142 to
work on uh any of the computers that we
have. So, we've gone for New Town as the
kind of backup option. But all of these
plans to use nuclear weapons as just
large bombs were very much real.
>> During the Cold War, there were numerous
numerous kinds of nuclear weapons and
tens of thousands of nuclear weapons
across the world um that were deployed
by Russia and the United States. And
within that, you had varying levels. The
Falcon A26A, for example, was a 1950s
air-to-air missile which operated on a
similar logic to nuclear depth charges.
It didn't matter if the missile you were
firing at an incoming Soviet bomber
wasn't particularly accurate if it was
fitted with a 1.5 kiloton nuclear
warhead.
[music]
In Culver City, California, the Falcon,
the US Air Force's newest guided
missile. An artist conception shows how
the electronic missile [music] is
launched and with a brain of its own
hunts out and destroys enemy bombers.
[music]
The same W54 warhead was also fitted
onto America's infamous M28 and M29 Davy
Crockett system, which allowed a team as
small as three to fire a relatively tiny
10-tonon nuke at the enemy. At certain
points, there were even ideas for
backpacks that had nuclear weapons where
a soldier would jump out of a plane to
be able to place a backpack under a
bridge and that would be the tactical
effect you're looking to achieve.
>> If the idea of using nuclear weapons
just like any other kind of weapon
sounds a little bit dicey, then
politicians, military leaders, and
others sometimes try and distinguish
between what they call strategic nuclear
weapons and so-called tactical nuclear
weapons. Strategic nukes are the massive
citybusting intercontinental ballistic
missiles we think of when we think of a
nuclear exchange between superpowers.
They're strategic because they're
designed to be used as a means of
strategic bombing, which is a bit of a
euphemism. Strategic bombing almost
always refers to the indiscriminate
bombing of large cities in order to try
and break citizens morale. A strategic
nuclear attack would mean the flattening
of a major city in the vein of America's
destruction of Hiroshima and Nagasaki at
the end of the Second World War. A
tactical nuke refers to the use of
nuclear weapons on the battlefield in
order to achieve much more limited
military objectives. An honest John
fired at an advancing division of tanks
or a Falcon A26A fired from a fighter
jet at a bomber. The very idea of a
tactical nuke might sound farical, but
from the early 1960s through to the
early 1990s, most of the nuclear weapons
which were in service at any one time
were tactical. The American truckloaded
Persing ballistic missiles stationed in
West Germany during the 1980s, for
example, weren't designed to flatten
Minsk. They were designed to take out
Soviet command stations in the event of
an invasion of Western Europe. In
reality though, this entire distinction
between strategic nuclear weapons and
tactical ones is kind of nonsense.
>> I mean, I suppose I feel like this is a
bit of a PR thing. Do you know what I
mean? To say, "Oh, these these little
tactical nuclear weapons are not as
dangerous as like the big strategic
nuclear weapons." But in reality, they
do the same thing.
>> I open the section by suggesting that we
were about to talk about small nukes,
which in reality is a little bit of a
lie. See, as I mentioned a moment ago,
what really separates strategic nuclear
weapons from tactical ones is not
firepower, but use. [music]
Tactical nuclear weapons often can be
smaller than strategic ones. But they
very much don't have to be. The original
Honest John's, for example, were larger
than the bomb dropped on Hiroshima.
Whilst the Persing ones were at least
four times as powerful with the
potential to be up to 26 times as
powerful. we'll release radioactive
fallout that will you know drift for for
miles and miles and miles um and will
you know have huge impact on our on our
ecosystems. [music] So whether they are
you know called tactical or whether
they're called strategic they they do
the same thing.
>> Even the smallest tactical nuclear
weapon ever built the Davy Crockett if
used would destroy a good chunk of the
Vatican city and kill a few hundred
people. This comes with the most obvious
risk that if you use it, you end up
killing or injuring a bunch of your own
troops alongside whatever enemy forces
you are hoping to incapacitate. Even if
you only take out the enemy, using
tactical nuclear weapons in any kind of
defensive capacity is likely to involve
setting off a nuclear bomb in either
your own country or that of an ally. A
Falcon A26A air-to-air missile might
help to destroy a Soviet bomber headed
for London, but you have just showered
half of Mar in nuclear radiation. The
very smallest nuclear weapons,
relatively speaking, thus came to be
retired as soon as missile and torpedo
guidance technology made it possible to
destroy enemy vehicles in more
intelligent ways than just throwing
nukes at them.
>> The Sparrow is a supersonic beam rider
using a solid propellant.
>> These are not weapons that can be used
in a kind of sort of a um a tactical way
as they call it. They they're not
precise weapons, you know what I mean?
>> The biggest pitfall to tactical nuclear
weapons, however, is outlined in this
essay published by Nina Tanamald in
1999. It outlines the idea of the
nuclear taboo. Tanamour suggests that at
the same time as the Honest John's and
Davy Crockett were being developed, so
too was emerging this idea that nuclear
weapons actually weren't like any other
weapon. The size of their firepower and
the unique side effect of radiation kind
of set them apart as another thing
entirely. Using a nuclear weapon
suddenly wasn't a good look. More than
this, the same nuclear taboo, which was
deterring one side from using nuclear
weapons, was also giving the other pause
for thought. The fear was that even just
using a cheeky little 0.02 kiloton Davy
Crockett in a localized battle might
break that taboo and set off a tit for
tat exchange of nuclear missiles, ending
with total mutual destruction. Anyway,
>> the problem with this is that it
actually lowers the threshold of nuclear
use where countries become more willing
and they consider nuclear use more
acceptable because it might
theoretically cause less damage than
maybe a multi-megaton warhead would.
[music] So, it's a really dangerous idea
to assume that a single warhead could be
used without incredible consequences and
ramifications or that its use could be
acceptable. It's for a mixture of all of
these reasons and more that ridding the
world of tactical nuclear weapons was
generally seen as a far greater priority
during the Cold War than ridding the
world of strategic ones. The vast bulk
of weapons which were dismantled in the
late 1980s and early 1990s were
tactical. The intermediate range nuclear
forces treaty, for instance, explicitly
sought to tackle weapons such as the
American Persings and Soviet RSD10s.
[music]
Regardless of how powerful they were,
and they were still plenty powerful, the
fear was that tactical weapons were far
more dangerous in their potential for
being the spark which lit the fuse of
nuclear war.
>> And that's part of what we're seeing
where norms are starting to erode across
the board with Russia threatening
nuclear use in Ukraine. Countries
increasing their nuclear rhetoric in an
attempt to signal. All of these things
are contributing to this idea that
nuclear use could be acceptable in
[music] low yield circumstances.
>> One of the most terrifying aspects in
current conversations surrounding
nuclear weapons then is that this
longestablished notion that nuclear
weapons need to be treated differently
to other kinds of weapons is gradually
being abandoned. We're seeing a
resurgence of conversations about low
yield nuclear weapons. Um, where
countries are seeking what they call
flexible response options to achieve
military or political objectives. The
F-35A fighter jets the UK is currently
looking at buying are not only notable
for being the first time [music] in more
than two decades that the British armed
forces will have the capability to drop
nuclear bombs rather than just its
Trident submarine program, but also
because where Trident is a strategic
system, the F-35A would be for tactical
use. The question is whether the
deployment of more low-yield weapons is
likely to increase the chances of them
actually being used and subsequently
whether the breaking of that nuclear
taboo through the use of just a little
nuke is likely to quickly lead to much
bigger weapons being used [music] too.
The end of the age of nuclear treaties
[music]
began with the death of this one, my
beloved anti-bballistic missile treaty.
>> In 2002, the United States withdrew from
the anti-bballistic missile treaty,
which influenced Russia and China in
developing and modernizing new nuclear
systems like hypersonics in order to
counter US missile defenses. So, that
kind of is where a lot of people say
things really started kicking off.
>> George Bush Jr.'s His rationale for
pulling out of the treaty was that with
the Cold War over, the main threat to
[music] peace and stability now came
from terrorists and rogue states who
would love to throw a missile at
America. The ABM, he warned, was holding
the US back from being able to defend
itself against future such attacks. No
one was entirely flippant about the
potential that the ripping up of the ABM
might come with negative consequences.
[music]
The US was fully expecting that in
response to it pulling [music] out of
that treaty, Russia would choose to pull
out of start 2, the followon treaty from
start one, which we mentioned earlier.
And [music] they do. The day after the
ABM is dead, so too is start. The
consolation is that George Bush Jr. and
Vladimir Putin opted in preparation to
sign this treaty, the strategic
offensive reductions treaty or sort,
which in truth is a bit of a sticking
plaster. For clarity, most of these
treaties which we have hanging up here,
we chose to print off fewer pages than
we maybe could have so that you know the
string would [music] stay standing up.
Sort is legitimately just over two
pages. It placed some limits on the
number of warheads which each country
could have deployed, [music] but still
allowed both signatories to keep as many
additional warheads as they liked in
storage. While there were still some
warheads being dismantled due to old
age, then the rate did begin to slow.
Nevertheless, with the war on terror
having replaced the Cold War as the key
narrative of global geopolitics,
relations between the world's two
foremost nuclear superpowers remained at
least warm. In fact, in April 2010,
Barack Obama and Dmit Medvidev signed
this bad boy, the New Start Treaty. The
one that I mentioned right back at the
beginning of this video,
>> the New Star Treaty.
>> This placed the strictest limits yet on
the number of nuclear weapons which each
country could have deployed. It also
allowed for continuous monitoring of the
other country to make sure that both
were playing ball.
>> And then you have New Start, of course,
which is it it places limits on deployed
US and Russian strategic launchers. and
it's been one of many in a series of
core strategic arms control
arrangements.
>> There were a really good 3 years here.
In February 2014, however, Russia
decided to invade [music] Ukraine for
the first time. Worse still, in late
2016, the Russian military announced
that it was working on reviving its
Iscanda M short-range ballistic [music]
missile program, marking a return of our
good old friend, the tactical nuke. Then
new President Donald Trump [music]
quickly declared that he felt this to be
a violation of the intermediate range
nuclear forces treaty from back in 1987.
>> So Europe was already pretty shaken up
at this point and [music] it proved to
be a key factor in a lot of the changes
that we're seeing today.
>> Very soon the INF was all but dead.
Something which would be confirmed 6
years later through the medium of
Twitter. all things. There remains some
hope that the US and Russia might be
brought back to the table to discuss an
extension [music] of New Start. There
was just one problem. Donald Trump
wanted to include China [music]
and China didn't want to play ball. Sort
the sticking plaster treaty that had
expired a long time ago by this point.
[music] And uh to be honest, Sort 2
never came into force. That really
should have just come down partway
through the previous [music] section
with a bit of string. Sorry about that.
There remain some nuclear treaties still
in place, limits [snorts] on testing and
on countries which aren't already
nuclear powers [music] being able to
become so. The strength of those really
relies on the strength of international
cooperation more broadly, which as
things stand isn't looking super strong.
[music]
What is clear is that the age of nuclear
treaties which place hard caps on the
number of nuclear weapons that different
countries are allowed to have appears to
be over.
That was harder than I thought it was
going to be. [music]
So yeah, the second really big thing
which has changed since the cold war is
China. China first became a nuclear
power in 1964, the fifth country to do
so and the last to be included as a
recognized nuclear state in the nuclear
non-prololiferation [music] treaty. For
a long time though, China's actual
nuclear arsenal wasn't all that much to
write home [music] about. When Bush and
Putin signed SAR back in 2002, China
didn't even receive a mention at the
press [music] conference. As recently as
2012, China had just 240 nuclear
warheads. That's fewer than the 300 held
by France and a minuscule amount in
comparison [music] to the nearly 5,000 a
piece stockpiled by the US and Russia.
Moreover, that number had been pretty
flat since the 1980s. This was at least
in part because of this statement.
Immediately after testing their first
atomic bomb in 1964, the Chinese
government immediately issued [music]
this statement, committing themselves to
a policy of no first use. They were
effectively saying that while they did
now have nuclear weapons, they would
only ever consider using them in
retaliation, never as an initial act of
aggression. in building their nuclear
arsenal. Then, China's approach has
largely been to maintain a nuclear
capability, which they describe as lean
and effective, enough to deter anyone
from launching a nuclear strike on them,
and no more. China has also repeatedly
attempted to get other countries to
adopt the same approach. Back in 1994,
[music]
China issued a draft treaty to the other
four nuclear powers, which if adopted,
would have made no first use a mutual
nuclear policy for [music] everyone. In
the years since, they have repeatedly
tried to make that the case. And yet,
all of this at the same time as they've
been massively expanding their nuclear
arsenal.
>> We're seeing China in particular build
up and expand its nuclear forces in a
way that is unprecedented. And this is a
cause for concern because we've
primarily placed limits on strategic
nuclear weapons through [music] a
bipolar in a bipolar world where it was
two countries who were able to work
towards communication, work towards, you
[music] know, building trust and good
faith measures, building predictability.
For decades and decades, it was just
those two countries trying to work
together to understand each other and to
agree to certain norms and and limits.
[music] And when you add a third country
into that mix, it complicates things
because each country believes it has to
defend against now two other
large arsenals. Between 2020 and 2025,
China's nuclear arsenal doubled from
around 300 warheads to 600. The US and
Russia still maintain the vast bulk of
the world's warheads, but China's
capability now far surpasses that of
France, the UK, and every other state.
Moreover, a far greater proportion of
China's weapons are actually deployed,
[music] whereas the majority of America
and Russia's remain in storage. The
addition of China to the equation isn't
just a case of [music] there being more
nuclear weapons in the world than there
might have been otherwise. It's also a
case that having three nuclear
superpowers [music]
just makes every aspect of all of this
all the more volatile. It makes agreeing
treaties much harder because now there
are three participants in any
negotiation rather than just two. It
also makes it much harder to avoid an
arms race as every time country A builds
its nuclear capacity in response to
country B, country C is likely to follow
suit as well.
>> It complicates this idea of building
trust and predictability when you have
an entire other country that operates
completely differently, has completely
different history and systems [music]
where and even priorities, right?
Russia's goals and priorities are not
the same as China's goals and priorities
are not the same as the US goals and
priorities. So you're trying to balance
all three of these. And I think when we
when we look to a future in which we are
in this multipolar situation, we see a
lot of new technologies entering the
scene, there could be opportunities for
some kind of threeway multipolar arms
control arrangement between China,
Russia, and the United States. But arms
control might have to look differently
than what we've seen it before.
>> Of course, all of this assumes that our
leaders are trying to avoid a nuclear
war. Most of us take it for granted that
our presidents and prime ministers
understands that winning a nuclear
conflict is impossible. [music] And yet,
what if that core tenant of nuclear
strategy is being forgotten?
Here
[music]
we go.
In the popular imagination, a nuclear
exchange [music] is just that. Country A
fires all of their nuclear weapons at
country B. Country B fires all of theirs
back. Maybe even country C gets
involved. The winner is essentially
whoever manages to fire more of their
weapons first. But what if there was
another way?
This is a video of Israel's Iron [music]
Dome air defense system. Iron Dome is
one of three complimentary systems
designed to protect Israel's urban areas
from rocket attack. Each system is able
to intercept missiles of varying ranges
before they land. The IDF claims that
Iron Dome in particular has an accuracy
rate of more than 90%. Having
intercepted thousands and thousands of
rockets, perhaps inspired by these
impressive statistics, Donald Trump
recently announced that he would be
building a similar system to protect the
American homeland. He called it Golden
Dome because of course he did. He says
that Golden Dome will involve both
physical interceptor devices and
high-powered lasers. and some of it will
be based [music] in space. It will also
involve artificial intelligence
integration because of course it will.
Initial cost estimates suggest that the
system is likely to cost up to $3.6
trillion. [music] And while Trump says
it will be finished by the end of this
presidential term, other commentators
are less sure it will ever [music] exist
at all. And that's because building this
kind of interceptor system to combat
nuclear attack is basically impossible.
When it comes to the issue of missile
defense, for instance, [music] when we
test missile defenses and when we look
at the effectiveness and accuracy, they
don't actually work that well. So, at
least with the the technology that we
have and the cost that it takes to have
effective missile defenses, you don't
necessarily need the newest technology
in order to evade them.
>> To anyone who was alive during the
1980s, the basic concept behind Golden
Dome might not sound all that new, and
that's because it's not. In 1984, Ronald
Reagan launched the Strategic Defense
Initiative, a very similar sounding plan
to make nuclear weapons obsolete with
proposals including both physical
interceptors and high-powered lasers,
some of which would be based in space.
[music] SDI wasn't, as Reagan might have
hoped, received with rapturous applause.
Tech Kennedy mockingly referred to the
scheme as Star Wars, a Monica, the SDI,
never really shook off. Critics who
didn't simply think that the whole thing
was ridiculous, worried that it might
inflame tensions, a period when the Cold
War was running particularly hot. Reagan
was adamant that the STI could be built
without the US breaking its commitments
under the anti-bballistic missile
[music] treaty. But both the USSR itself
and many within America, who wanted to
avoid nuclear war, viewed it as a
provocation the world just didn't
[music] need. So, I think a lot of this
goes back to what I mentioned a little
bit before with the US withdrawal from
[music] the anti-bballistic missile
treaty in 2002 where ballistic missile
defenses are unfettered. You know,
theoretically you could you could have
as many as you wanted, right? This
raises concerns from other countries in
their ability to hold the United States
or whoever [music] at risk. that the
strategic defense initiative was a
complete and total failure is evident in
the fact that just a few years later,
Reagan [music] was back at the
negotiating table working on the First
START treaty. The program had proven too
expensive and continued to show few
signs that it would even be successful.
It wasn't until after it had pulled out
of the anti-bballistic missile treaty in
the early 2000s [music] that the US
would finally gain a defense system
theoretically capable of defending
against [music] intercontinental
ballistic missiles. And even then, the
so-called groundbased [music] midcourse
defense system is both extremely
expensive, extremely limited, and pretty
debatable in its efficacy. [music] It
cost at least $90 billion over the 20
years of its development and still has a
success rate of just 55% during highly
controlled tests. Worse still, the
system tops out at just 44 missiles.
[music] Should an all-out nuclear war
break out, the US has just 44 chances to
maybe stop [music] less than 50
missiles.
>> These systems don't work. You know, they
have a very, very low, you know, success
rate, it is literally a bullet hitting a
bullet.
>> The problem is that as simple as it
might sound to [music] simply build a
bigger version of the Iron Dome, the
idea doesn't really scale up. Israel is
tiny, smaller even than it thinks, while
America is a whole continent. More than
this, the weapons that the Iron Dome is
set to defend against are much smaller
and shorter range than those which would
likely be used against the US. [music]
And even that has cost billions and
billions of dollars. None of this, of
course, has stopped Trump and his
Secretary of War, Pete Hexath, from
continuing to talk up the potential of
the system. All we care about is
protecting the homeland. President Trump
has said for a long time, defense of the
homeland is critical. America first,
America and Americans. Golden Dome is a
generational investment in that to
ensure we keep our people safe. That's
it. The Pentagon has announced awards of
contracts to over [music] 1,000
companies who may end up working on the
system. Small contracts have reportedly
been awarded to Northrup [music] Grman,
True Anomaly, Loheed Martin, and Andril
to build work on proposed systems. To
bring this video full circle, [music]
General Michael Gwetlin of the US Space
Force has compared the system to the
Manhattan project.
>> This is on order of magnitude of the
Manhattan project. Uh it's going to take
a concerted uh uh effort from the very
top of of our government uh is going to
take a national will to bring all this
together.
>> And yet even exactly what this is at the
most basic level remains to be seen.
Complicating all of this is the fact
that an eternal truth of nuclear
politics is that bluster, saber
rattling, and so-called posturing are a
core part of the game. [music]
Even the ambition to build a golden dome
might project strength abroad and
comfort at home.
Ah, we go again.
There are plenty of Reagan stands out
there who will continue to argue that
Star Wars was actually an ingenious
negotiating tactic designed to force
concessions from the Soviets. As those
involved in the drafting of the
anti-bballistic missile treaty knew way
back in the 1970s, however, there is a
danger to projecting too much strength.
[music] It risks exacerbating tensions
at a time when we are already looking
like we might be in the beginnings of an
arms race. [music] Because of this,
countries are developing capabilities
that allow them to potentially bypass
missile defenses. So whether it's
hypersonics, you know, HGVs, cruise
missiles, um a lot of these capabilities
have existed in the past, but developing
them, deploying them, and implementing
them in ways that uh seem to provide an
advantage to the country that has them.
The real risk, however, isn't that
Donald Trump convinces you or Vladimir
Putin or Xi Jinping that the Golden Dome
works. The real risk is that he
convinces himself.
The manner in which politicians and
military leaders started talking about
nuclear weapons in recent years has
taken a significant turn. Way back at
the height of the Cold War, the one
thing really holding them [laughter]
back was that a principle of mutually
assured destruction. An era in which
Donald Trump or anyone else feels like
they can use nuclear weapons with
impunity is one in which that option is
going to look increasingly tempting.
Right.
That was fun while that lasted.
Okay, so I lied to you. Earlier on, I
promised to tell you a bunch of things
which had changed between the previous
nuclear age and this one. And that is
kind of what this video has been about.
In truth though, most of the things
which are currently propelling us
towards [music] potential nuclear war
today are a result of forgetting lessons
which we already learned during the
height of the Cold War. We know that
so-called tactical nuclear weapons such
as those which could be dropped by the
F-35A fighter jets the UK is currently
buying are incredibly dangerous. We know
that missile defense systems like Golden
Dome really work. You don't have to have
seen war games to know that winning a
nuclear exchange is all but impossible.
>> Strange game. The only winning move is
not to play. The only way we've ever
managed to reduce nuclear risk is
through diplomacy. And at the moment,
not only is that kind of diplomacy not
happening, but the concept of diplomacy
itself is being viewed as foolish and
naive. The potential consequences of
that are absolutely terrifying.
As treaties expire and countries shift
towards rearmament, a whole economy of
arms production is being rekindled. The
Ministry of Defense here in the UK is
set to invest an extra4.4 billion pounds
into the Devport dockyard over the next
decade. If you want to learn more about
the actual logistics of arms production,
you'd love the logistics of arms
manufacturing, the sixth episode in the
logistics of X, a series by the team
behind Wendover Productions, which
uncovers the inner workings of various
different industries, including defense,
fishing, and the harsh. The logistics of
X is available to watch exclusively on
Nebula, the premium streaming service
created by myself and a bunch of other
clever creators. It's just one show in
an everexpanding catalog of exclusive
films and [music] series which are only
available to watch on Nebula. I'm
currently really enjoying Taramoon's
Nebula exclusive series politics. It's a
really fun and funny dive into the
politics of breasts [music] and the
history thereof. It's a perfect example
of why Nebula is so great for both
audiences and creators. If Tara had made
politics and just put it up on YouTube,
I think we all know what the chances of
it actually turning up in anyone's
recommendations feeds would have been.
Nebula allows us as creators to make
shows for you as viewers without having
to worry about whether any
recommendations or monetization feeds
are going to hide them away. More than
this, in an era where YouTube has become
more and more clickbaity, our goal with
Nebula is to make a genuinely prestige
experience where you can actually find
something highquality and enriching to
watch without wasting a million hours
scrolling through slop. All of us
involved in creating Nebula are viewers
as well as creators, and we want it to
be a high-quality experience. We also
want it to be affordable. In fact, if
you sign up using my link,
go.bula.tv/tomnicholas,
you'll get 50% off an annual plan, which
brings the cost down to just $2.50 per
month. And we also now take pound
sterling, in which case it will cost you
£2.50 a month, which is an absolute
steal. Alongside being a fantastic
package of stuff to watch, signing up to
Nebula using my link
go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas
really does help to support the channel
at a time when making videos for the
internet is getting harder and harder.
Not only do we get paid more every time
you watch our videos on Nebula rather
than on YouTube, but I also get a little
kickback when you sign up using that
link, which is really helpful, too. That
link again is go.nebula.tv/tomicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again and I'll see you over on Nebula.
All that's left for me to do is to say a
massive thank you to the people who
support my work by being signed up to
the top tier of my Patreon over at
patreon.com/tomicholas.
Those people are Richard Gary Dick on
Spain, Bill Mitchell, ZedC Reese, Zoe
Alden, Alexander Blank, Neil Zildgard,
Sophia R, Sergio Suarez, Richard Rapun,
Amit Singh, Parahard, Gabriel Ko, Fiasco
Linguini, Agent Maxwell, Glenn Sugdan,
Emil Jarabar, Yillimson, Paulus Edus,
Sam Forinato, Sandre Yen, Douglas
Urquart, Ahmed Harachic, and Hast.ie.
Thank you so much to all those people.
If you'd like to find out how you can
join them in supporting my work, you can
find out how to do so over at
patreon.com/tomnicholas.